Guide to the George J. Peirce Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George J. Peirce papers
1905-1926
SC0026
Peirce, George J. (George James), 1868?-1954.
0.75 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1965.
Information about Access
None.
Biography
Peirce earned his B.S. at Harvard in 1890 and his M.A. and Ph.D. from the University of Leipzig, 1894. He taught at Indiana University before coming to Stanford University in 1897 as assistant professor of botany. He was appointed professor in 1910 and served as executive head of the department from 1925 until his retirement in 1933. He was the author of three textbooks on plant physiology and coauthor with three other Stanford faculty of a textbook in general biology. He was active in the civic life of Palo Alto and involved in conservation issues.
Scope and Content
Peirce's papers are primarily incoming and outgoing correspondence pertaining to his professional interests (research, publications, teaching positions) and his administrative duties at Stanford. Correspondents include Daniel T. MacDougal, William Austin Cannon, Charles R. Barnes, John M. Coulter, William F. Ganong, and Raymond H. Pond. Also of note is correspondence with the Forest Service regarding Peirce's study of the effects from smelter fumes, 1910; and correspondence with Wesley H. Beach, Lyman V. W. Brown, and A. W. Maltby pertaining to various legal cases regarding plant damage from cement dust. His Stanford correspondence includes letters from David Starr Jordan; letters from LeRoy Abrams, with a report on the Dudley Herbarium; and Peirce's letters to J. C. Branner (1910-1915) discussing theft of departmental microscopes, with reports on the work of the botany department.
Collection Contents
- Incoming Correspondence, 1905-1926
  - Abrams, LeRoy, 3 letters, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen, C. E., 3 letters, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A, 1907-1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - All Saints' Church, rector of, 1907
    - Andrews, Frank M., 1911
    - Anderson, P. J., 1910
  - Barnes, C. R., 8 letters, 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bausch and Lomb Optical Co., 6 letters, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beach, Wesley H., 27 letters, 1909-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brown, Lyman Van Wickle, 16 letters, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B, 1905-1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bermingham, Jr., John, 1909
    - Bessey, Charles E., 1910
    - Beveridge, Horatio, 1906
    - Birge, E. A., 1911
    - Blodgett, B., undated
    - Boring, Ora, 1906
    - Boyd, John D., 2 letters, 1905
    - Branner, J. C., 1911
    - Brannon, M. A., 2 letters, 1910-1912
    - Braun, Knecht, Heimann Co., 2 letters, 1910-1912
    - Britton, N. L., 1910
    - Brown, Louis Francis, 1906
    - Burlingame, L. L., 1913
    - Burnight, T. S., 3 letters, 1908
  - Campbell, D. H., 4 letters, 1906 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Institute of Washington, 1905-1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 5 letters from Gilbert, M. M., 1905-06
    - 1 letter from Woodward, R. S., 1906
    - 24 letters from MacDougal, D. T., 1908-1911
    - 12 letters from Cannon, W. A., 1908 and 1911-1912
  - Clark, G. A., 9 letters and 1 card, 1906-1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Coulter, John M., 7 letters, 1908-1912 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - C, 1905-1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - California Nursery Co., 1911
    - Cattell, J. McK, with pamphlet on "University Control,", 1911
    - Chamberlain, J. P., 1906
    - Clark, G. T., 2 letters, 1910 and 1924
    - Copeland, Edwin B., 1906
    - Couch, E. J., 1911
    - Couch, Mary Y, 1910
    - Cubberley, Ellwood P., 1906
    - Curtis, [?], biology librarian, to Committee on Library and Store Room with copies of: letter to Dr. R. L. Wilbur from the Committee, minutes of the Committee meeting, and minutes of the Biology Library and Store Room Committee meeting, 1925, 1926; 1926; 1926
  - D, 1906-1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Danforth, C. H., 1925
    - Davieson, Edward, with requisition sheet and 3 pamphlets on microscopes, 1910
    - Davis, Horace, 1912
    - Doane Gas Regulators, 2 letters, 1912
    - Dole, Charles F. [to D. S. Jordan], 1906
    - Donath, August, 1911
    - Durand, W. F., 4 letters, 1906-1907
    - Dutton, Harry A., 2 letters, with clipping on redwood trees, Redwood City, 1911-1912
  - Forest Service, 12 letters, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - To the Forrester from F. E. Olmsted
    - To District Forrester from A. K. Chittenden
    - From Swift Berry
    - From T. D. Woodbury
    - From G. de S. Canavarro
    - From Louis Margolin
    - From Austin Ceary
    - From A. B. Patterson
    - From R. Y. Stuart
    - From J. S. Wamu
  - E-F, 1905-1911 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Elliott, O. E., 2 letters, 1905-1907
    - Farmer, J. B., [1910]
    - Farrand, Max, 1911
    - Fisher, Carl W., 3 letters, with a monthly statement, 1906-1907
    - Franklin, Sara, to [Dr. Snow?], undated
    - Freer, Paul C., to Director of Civil Service, 1911
  - Ganong, William F., 3 letters, 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - G, 1906-1912 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Grant, J. D., 1911
    - Grinnell, Joseph, 1906
    - Grotophorst, W., 3 letters, 1911-1912
  - Harper, R. A., 6 letters, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - H, 1905-1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hammond, Howard, 2 letters, 1910
    - Hand, J. W., 1908
    - Hardy, Lowell E., 1911
    - Harvey, R. B., 2 letters, 1924
    - Herre, Albert C., 1910
    - Hirn, K. E., postcard, 1906 or 1908
    - Hollman, [?], 1913
    - Hopkins, Timothy, 1905
    - Houston, David F., 1907
    - Howard, L. O., 1911
    - Hulbert, A., 1910
    - Hungate, Jesse A., 1910
    - Hutchinson, Arthur J., 2 letters, 1910-1911
  - Jolivette, Holly D. M., 7 letters, 1910 and undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jordan, David Starr, 12 letters, 1905-1913 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - J-L, 1906-1922 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Jeffrey, E.C., 3 letters, 1908-1910
    - Jesse, R. H., 2 letters, 1908
    - Kelley, W. H., to Chief Forester, 1910
    - [Karsten, J.] to [Herr Kollege] in German, 1910
    - Landrum, J. M., 1922
    - Lyons, Frank, 1906
  - M-N, 1909-1926 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - McIntyre, Frank, 1911
    - Maltby, A. W., 2 letters, 1909-1910
    - Martin E. G, 2 letters with enclosure, 1925-26
    - Merrill, E. D., 3 letters to B. M. Duggan, R. A. Harper, and Peirce, 1911
    - Montana, Univ. of, signed "Clyde" from president's office, 1912
    - Montgomery, C. P. [to G. A. Clark], 1910
    - Newcombe, F. C., 1910
  - Pond, Raymond H., 3 letters, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - O-R, 1905-1926 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Overton, J. B., 1911
    - Palo Alto Gas Co., 1910
    - Pinchot, Clifford, 1910
    - Public Health Committee (S.U.), 2 letters, 1905
    - Purington and Adair, 1911
    - Putnam, E. K., 2 letters, 1905
    - Robinson, Edgar, 1926
    - Roth, A. E., 1920
  - S-W, 1906-1925 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Scott, Leonard L. [to L. L. Burlingame], 1912
    - Shaw, Walter R., 1906
    - Shreve, Forrest, 1910
    - Shull, Charles A., 1924
    - Smith, [?]ward, 1911
    - Spalding, V. M, 2 letters, 1910
    - Spencer Lens Company [to L. L. Burlingame], letter and telegram, 1910
    - Stanf, Ida, 2 letters, 1906 and undated
    - Stow, Vanderlynn, 1911
    - Waters, H. J., 2 letters and 1 telegram, 1908
    - Wesley and Son, William, 2 letters, 1910
    - Weymouth, F. W., 1925
    - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1916
    - Wiltz, Bertha A., 1910
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1926
  - Allen, C. E., 6 letters, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bausch and Lomb Optical Co., 4 letters, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Beach, W. H., 15 letters, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Branner, J. C., 12 letters, 1915 and undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Brown, L. V. W., 20 letters, with several pages of misc. notes and a statement of indebtedness, 1910-1912 and nd (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A-B, 1906-1915 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Alden, 1912
    - Anderson, P. J., 1910
    - Andrews, Frank M., 2 letters, 1911
    - Barnes, C. R., 2 letters, 1906-1908
    - Bergen, 1911
    - Bessey, Charles E., 1910
    - Birge, E. A., 1911
    - Blakeslee, 1912
    - Blodgett, B., 1912
    - Boring, Ora, 1912
    - Brannon, M. A., 2 letters, 1910-1912
    - Braun, Knecht, Heimann Co., 2 letters, 1911
    - Britton, N. L., 1910
    - Bureau of Insular Affairs, 1911
    - Burlingam, L. Lance, 1913
    - Burnight, T. S., 4 letters, 1908
  - Cannon, W. A., 13 letters, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clark, G. A., 27 letters, 1910-1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Coulter, J. M., 12 letters, 1908-1912 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - C-E, 1905-1924 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - California Nursery Co., 1912
    - Campbell, D. H., 2 letters, 1910 and 1914
    - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 2 letters, 1905-1906
    - Cary, Austin, 1910
    - Cattell, J. McK., 3 letters, 1911-1912
    - Clark, G. T., 1924
    - Couch, E. J., 1911
    - Davis, [Horace], 2 letters, 1912
    - Doane Gas Regular Co., 4 letters, 1912
    - Dudley, W. R., 1910
    - Dutton, Harry A., 3 letters, 1911-1912
    - Eberly, W. V., 1911
  - Harper, R. A., 4 letters, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jordan, David Starr, 19 letters, 1906-1912 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - F-J, 1906-1911 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Farlow, Dr., 1909
    - Farmer, J. Bretland, 1910
    - Forestor, The, with two enclosed letters to Woodbury and Patterson, 1910
    - Franklin, [Sara], 1906
    - Grotophorst, W., 1911
    - Hand, J., with enclosure, 5 letters, 1910-1911
    - Heald, 1911
    - Helena National Forest Supervisor, 1910
    - Herre, Albert C., 1910
    - Heynemann and Son, Inc., Herman, 1910
    - Holt and Co., Henry, 1911
    - Houston, David F., (2 copies), 1907
    - Howard, L. O., 1911
    - Hutchinson, Captain, 2 letters with newspaper clipping, 1910
    - James, 1910
    - Jeffrey, E. C., 3 letters, 1908-1909
    - Jesse, R. H., 1908
    - Jolivette, Holly D. M., 1910
  - MacDougal, D. T., 18 letters, 1909-1911 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Maltby, A. M., 4 letters, 1909-1911 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - K-O, 1905-1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Kollege, Herr, in German, 1910
    - McCaffrey, 1911
    - Martin, E. C., 1905
    - Merrill, E. D., 1911
    - Metcalf, P. W., 1912
    - Montana, U. of to "Clyde", 1912
    - Morse and Co., C. C., 2 letters, 1911-1912
    - M., 1926
    - Newcombe, F. C., 2 letters, 1910
    - Orange Growers' Association, 10 pages holograph notes re the association, 1910
    - Ott, N. H., 1910
    - Overton, J. B., 3 letters, 1911-1912
  - P-R, 1906-1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Palo Alto Board of Trustees, undated
    - Palo Alto Gas Company, 1910
    - Payette, Charles A., 1911
    - Pinchot, Clifford, 1910
    - Ramsay, M. M., 8 receipts, 1906-1907
    - Registrar, U. of Wisconsin, 1910
    - Rich, 1910
    - Roth, A. E., 1920
  - Spalding, V. M., 6 letters, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 5 letters, 1917-1924 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - S-W, 1906-1926 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Scott, Leonard L., with enclosure, 1912
    - Shaw, Walter R., 1906
    - Shreve, Forrest, 1911
    - Smith, Prof., 2 letters, 1911
    - Waters, H. J., 2 letters, 1908
    - Weigel, Oswald, 3 letters in German, 1910-1911
    - Wesley and Son, William, enclosed note, 1910
    - Widenham, A. W., 2 letters, 1925-1926
    - Wing, 1911
    - Woodward, 1911
  - Duplicate letters, and letter fragments, 1907-1913 (Box 2, Folder 15)